<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on the Short history of standing armies in England, in vindication of His Majesty and government with some animadversions on a paper, entituled, Considerations upon the choice of a speaker.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58369</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12827328</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94284</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248544589</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10551</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12827328</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94284)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on the Short history of standing armies in England, in vindication of His Majesty and government with some animadversions on a paper, entituled, Considerations upon the choice of a speaker.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Trenchard, John, 1662-1723. --  Short history of standing armies in England.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Considerations upon the choice of a speaker of the House of Commons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Standing army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94284:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94284:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS ON THE <hi>Short History</hi> OF Standing Armies IN ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>In Vindication of His <hi>Majesty</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Some Animadversions on a Paper, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Considerations upon the Choice of a Speaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—En quo discordia Cives</l>
               <l>Perduxit miseros —</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Virg. Ecl. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:94284:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94284:2"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE repeated Attempts of a Restless Party to embroil these Nations in New Contests with their Soveraign, make it the indispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Duty of every good Subject to contribute his Mite to the Common Repose, and to the creating of a good Understanding betwixt Prince and People. As in the Natural, so in the Politick Body, all Obstructions of a Mutual Communication of Friendly Influence betwixt the Head and the Members, tend to the Dissolution and Destruction of the whole; therefore it is absolutely necessary to apply timely Remedies to such a Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Distemper. It is not the Design of the following Sheets to prescribe the Antichristian Recipe of <hi>utere jure tuo Caesar,</hi> though sometimes it may be absolutely necessary in Government, as well as in Chirurgery, to practise the Maxim of
<q>
                  <l>—Immedicabile Vulnus,</l>
                  <l>Ense recidendum ne pars sincera trahatur.</l>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:94284:3"/> The Author wishes the Conversion, not the Destruction of the Opposite Party, and that they would apply Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials, and not Corrosives to Three Languishing Nations, whose Divisions have well-nigh undone them already. They may rest assured that he hath no Prejudice against their Persons whatever dislike he entert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their Principles; and that as he is under no Obligation to the Present Government by Place of Profit or Trust, he does not engage in the Controversie either out of a desire or expectation of other Reward, but that of a Good Conscience, in doing his Endeavours, as People ought to do in a General Conflagration, to extinguish the Flames that threaten our Destruction. He wishes that the Persons whom he opposes may Act from Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples equally harmless, and submits his hasty Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Censure of the Publick, for whose Service they are wholly design'd.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94284:3"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON THE History of Standing Armies IN <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Authors of the History of the Standing Army, lay down this Excellent Proposition in their Preface, That <hi>the whole Mystery of Government is to make the Interest of the Governours and Governed the same.</hi> But the Difficulty is how to convince those concerned, that it is so, and to bring them to a right Understanding of what is really their joint Interest; for sometimes one, sometimes both, are mistaken in that Point, as may be easily evinc'd by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Instances. The People of <hi>England</hi> judg'd truly that it was their Interest to have had the Bill of Exclusion pass against the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> but the Court thought the contrary. His Present Majesty judg'd truly, that it was his and the Nation's joint Interest that his Protestant Subjects of all Denominations should be rendred equally capable of serving him in Places of Power and Trust; but hitherto the Parliament have thought the contrary. It were the Interest of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and their Subjects too, to embrace the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94284:4"/> as might be easily demonstrated; but hitherto both the Governours and Governed have judg'd otherwise.</p>
            <p>So that tho' the Rule be true, yet both Rulers and People are often mistaken in the Application of it, and make their Humour their Interest; which can be ascrib'd to no other Cause, but the general Weakness and Corruption of Mankind, tho' our Author seems to deny it in the beginning of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, upon what Account, or from what Principle, is best known to himself. Nor is this Opinion of the Depravation of Men, chargeable with that lazy Consequence they fasten upon it, <hi>That therefore People submit patiently to their Countries Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and think a Reformation impossible;</hi> on the contrary they ought to take the more Care to guard against publick Mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, as they generally do in all Revolutions and new Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, because the Corruption of Mankind must be restrained by the Fetters of Law, and have been thus effectually restrain'd in all Ages, when such Laws have been daily put in execution, as History and Experience testifie.</p>
            <p>But to come closer to our Authors. What if it should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that they act contrary to this Rule themselves, by suggesting such Miscarriages in the present Administration, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to that bad End of Perswading the People that the present Government carries on a distinct Interest from theirs, when no such thing can be demonstrated? Certainly such a Practise is against the Interest both of the Governours and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned: Nor is it a probable way of obtaining Redress from a Parliament, which they tell us is the <hi>Fountain Head from whence the People expect all their Happiness, and Redress of Grievances,</hi> to insinuate that they are chosen by <hi>external Force</hi> or <hi>Bribery.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does it seem to carry any great sign of Affection to His Majesty, to tell the People that the Parliament is the Fountain from whence they must expect all their Happiness. Time was when our Parliament could have but done very little towards our Relief, if he had not come in to their Assistance; and seeing he was so kind and generous then, when he had no other Concern in us but a remote Prospect of Succession, and the Preservation of our Religion and Liberties, why should
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94284:4"/> he be excluded now from making up part of the <hi>Fountain</hi> at least, whence we are to hope for <hi>Relief</hi> and <hi>Redress?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Authors say true, That most of our Grievances and Corruptions are owing to King <hi>Charles</hi> II. being allowed a mercenary Army, and such large Revenues, as enabled him both to make use of Force and Bribery, in choosing Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Men, and bringing Parliaments to a Compliance: But what Comparison is there betwixt that Reign and this? Does not the World know that that Prince had no such Occasion for either as this Government hath had, and still has? He talk'd indeed of an actual War with <hi>France,</hi> but 'twas no longer than till he had actually got Money out of our Pockets But it's plain we had an actual and tedious War now, which could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been carried on without Money.</p>
            <p>This Insinuation, that the Great Offices of State were better in the Hands of the Nobility, and of single Persons, than in the Hands of Commoners, and those of Five, Seven, Nine, Fourteen, Ten, Eight, Sixteen, Two, and Four at a time, as the Treasury, Admiralty, Customs, Excise, Navy-Office, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are now managed, does not seem to be very favourale to their pretended Design of the Peoples Interest, which certainly is better consulted, by distributing profitable Offices amongst as many of 'em as possible, than by enriching One Person with an overgrown Sallary; and besides, it is the Dictate both of Scripture and Reason, That in the Multitude of Counsellors there is Safety; otherwise, if we may be allowed to compare small Things with great, our Author's Argument will plead as strongly for absolute Monarchy, without the Assistance of a Parliament, as for having those Offices he speaks of entrusted in the Hands of single Persons. I am far from thinking they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd the Friends of Despotical Power so much Kindness as to argue for them, because it is plain, that the Blow is aim'd at the present Government; for speaking of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. they say, <hi>He had not Places enough in his Disposal to secure a Majority in the House; for in those early Days the Art was not found out, of split<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and multiplying Places; as instead of a Lord-Treasurer, to have Five Lords of the Treasury,</hi> &amp;c. Envy and Malice knows no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94284:5"/> Bounds, but is so directly opposite to Charity, that thinks no Evil, that it will be sure to put the worst Sense upon every thing it will bear. Good Nature and untainted Loyalty would put a Construction of a contrary Tendency, upon this Practice of the present Government, that whereas former Governours, who design'd to swallow up Property by Prerogative, did all they could to render their Ministers as Despotical in their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Stations, as themselves; and that they might have the fewer Witnesses of their Designs to bereave the People of their Money and Liberty, put the chief Places of Profit and Trust, into as few Hands as they could: The present Governour, who came to redress the Grievances committed by his Predecessors, takes a contrary Method, and is willing that those Offices of Power and Trust should be entrusted in more Hands, that the People might be better secur'd against the Bribery of the Court, or a Foreign Potentate, than they were in former Reigns, it being highly improbable that Seven Lords of the Admiralty would connive at sending our Naval Stores, Ammunition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to our Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> though One Lord-Admiral did, and so of the rest, it being certainly much harder to Debauch so many, than to Debauch One; and if Care be taken to fill those Places with Gentlemen of true English Principles, as many of those at least who enjoy them at present are known to be; the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Number of such Persons entrusted, the more is the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on secur'd.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen's Argument that when these Offices were manag'd by Lords, the Commons were severe Inquisitors into their Actions, is no very friendly Discovery, nor does it any ways seem to be calculated for promoting a good Understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betwixt the Two Houses, no more than betwixt the Lords and the King, who is hereby accused of giving that away from them, which according to our Authors they might well plead as their own by Prescription; seeing they would seem to say, that <hi>this,</hi> and other things they there mention, <hi>was the English Government from the time of the Romans to that of King</hi> Charles I. But as to the force of the Argument, they would do well to produce their Reasons, why the Commons should not be as severe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94284:5"/> Inquisitors into the Actions of some of their own Number, seeing he himself tells us that the Advancement of <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Noy</hi> by King <hi>Charles</hi> I. served only to Exasperate the rest of the Commons, because he had not Places enough for all that expected them, nor Money enough to bribe them; it being equally impossible for his present Majesty to provide Places for all of the Commoners that may now expect them, or to find Money enough to bribe them, except he should <hi>split</hi> all the Places of Power and Trust in the Kingdom <hi>in Infinitum,</hi> as our Authors say; but then I am afraid that no Body would think them a Bribe worth the accepting, and so it may ease them of the Horror which they say they are so much troubled with, to think what danger this [splitting of Places] may be to our Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. But to return to the Argument of our Authors again. Let them oblige the World with their Reasons why those Commons that are disappointed of their Expectations of Places and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney now, should not be as severe Inquisitors into the Actions of those that have been happier, as to that Matter, than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, as the Commons were into those of <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Noy,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I.</p>
            <p>I must also beg leave of our Authors, to remark by the way, that notwithstanding their mighty Kindness to the People of <hi>England,</hi> and their Zeal for their Liberties and Laws, they seem to deal very unkindly with those Noble Patriots, that asserted our Liberties in 1641. when they reflect upon 'em as being exasperated because they had not the Money and Places they expected. What could the most imbittered Cavalier have said more? This is in downright Terms to accuse them of the most abominable Hypocrisie, and Rebellion, that ever was in the World. Whether this was the Design of our Authors or only an advised dash of their Pen, I know not; but I am afraid there's a Snake in the Grass, when neither the Patriots of those, nor of these times escape their Lash. That Parliament which Res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cued the Expiring Liberties of the Nation, did it because the King did not bribe them; and the bravest Prince in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse, who hath not only Rescued Three Nations, but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion, and the Common Liberty of <hi>Europe,</hi> must be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94284:6"/> slily accus'd of bribing his Parliaments, to carry on an Interest distinct from that of his People.</p>
            <p>Our Authors are mighty solicitous to think <hi>what will become of our Liberty, if in Ages to come all the Places should be given to Parliament Men. What shall be done</hi> (say they) <hi>when the Criminal becomes the Judge, and the Malefactors are left to try themselves? We may be sure their Common Danger will Unite them, and they will all Stand by one another.</hi> The Country will be Unhappy indeed if that ever come to be the Case; but as I have seen the same Charge, or one much like it, in other Pamphlets against the Age that now is, if our Authors think that the Charge is true, it had been more Ingenuous in them to speak out boldly, and not to lay the Plot in Ages to come. I am as far from appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving such an Abuse, as they or any Men alive, it being highly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable that a King should have the Legislative Power so much at Command, by making Members of the House of Commons, when he has such an Interest in the Upper House by his Domesticks, Officers of State, by creating new Lords, and making new Bishops, upon every Vacancy: But why all this Clamour against the present Government? Have not many of those Officers who have been formerly, or are now chosen Members of Parliament, deserved well both of their Prince and Country? And is it not possible that they can be true to the one, without betraying the other? I will put the Case, that his Majesty should have kept up the Army of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunteers that assembled to assist him at the Revolution, or at least as many of them as would have been willing to have continued in Arms till their own and the common Interest of <hi>Europe</hi> had been secur'd, which many are of Opinion had in that Case been much sooner and easier effected, could Offices Civil and Military have been more deservedly bestow'd, than upon those Gentlemen that ventur'd their Lives and Estates in so good a Cause; And must none of those have been chosen Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Men, because they were in Office under the King? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they cannot but own the Absurdity of such a Consequence. But to come nearer them, it has been observ'd by some (truly, or otherwise, I shall not determine) that in many Places where
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94284:6"/> the Clergy had most Interest, such Men have been chosen, as are commonly reputed Jacobites, or that way inclin'd; and its but reasonable to believe it, because that Order of Men was univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally tainted with the Doctrines of Nonresistance, and Passive-Obedience; and those that continue so, must needs be Enemies to the present Constitution. Then, supposing it to be so, and considering the Interest the Clergy have in <hi>England,</hi> are any Men more like to be a Balance to Jacobites of their chusing, and to oppose their sly and unfriendly Motions in Parliament, than those that are engaged by Interest, as well as Affection, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his Majesty's Title.</p>
            <p>From all which it is easie to inferr, that these Gentlemen, and others whose have writ of the same Side, ought to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish betwixt Times and Seasons. In the late Reigns the Court aim'd visibly at the Subversion of our Religion and Liberties, and therefore it was dangerous indeed to the Nation to chuse those that had Places and Offices under the Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause generally none were employ'd by it but such as concurr'd in the same mischievous Design: But can Malice it self say any such thing of this Government? Hath not his present Majesty restor'd us to our ancient Liberty, and secur'd us from the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that threatned our Religion? Whence then do all these Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies of the Court now arise? Either they must proceed from the Papists and Jacobites, or from those that are Enemies to Kingly Government, or from both; And is not this a surprizing Conjunction of Two such opposite Parties? The Jacobites indeed, act answerably to their Principles in so doing, for they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of Opinion, that Kingly Government, and a Lineal Succession, are <hi>Jure divino,</hi> both which have been so exploded since the Revolution, that they are only fit to be entertain'd by Men who have lost their Reason; but for any of those call'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths-men who, though they think that Form the best, yet always profess it as their Opinion, that they ought to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to any Species of Magistracy that answers the Ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; It is mighty strange that any of them should now fall in with the Jacobites to render the present Government un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>easie. It might have been reasonably hop'd, that their being
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94284:7"/> dropp'd by the Jacobites, last Session, in the Matter of Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the Militia, in Hopes of which, some of 'em had been inveagl'd to concur against the Standing Army, should have now convinc'd them of their Mistake, and created in 'em a generous Contempt of that mischievous Party, whose Name ought to be held in Execration by all that wish well to their Country, and the Protestant Religion, or that can remember their late Horrid Plot to Assassinate His Majesty, and bring in a French Army. Who then can have Patience to hear some, who pretend to be of opposite Principles, applaud the Choice of such Persons for Parliament Men, and express their Hopes of any thing that is good to the Nation from them?</p>
            <p>I know their principal Reason of joining with them, is, that they think they will oppose a Standing Army, and the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of those who have Places of Power and Trust under his Majesty for Members of Parliament; and that some of them are sensible too, that the Jacobites do this only to make way for the Return of the late King: Whereas they on the other hand oppose those things in this Reign, because they may be drawn into President in others, which the People may perhaps have no such Reason to trust. But then should they do Evil, that Good may come of it; should they unhinge and shake a good Government, because they are afraid they may fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a bad one, Is not that the natural way to bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the thing they fear? Suppose the present Government should be disabled by with-holding of Money, and denying it a Competent Land-Force, to support it self; and in that Case, that a French and Irish Army should again be invited over by our Jacobites, as formerly, and land upon upon us, whether do they think that the Commonwealth, or the Jacobite Party, would be most likely to prevail? Would they not find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves oblig'd in Honour and Conscience to espouse King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi>'s Cause in that Case? Could they find such another Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral for Authority, or Experience, to fight under? Why then should they take such Methods as naturally tend to bring us to that unhappy Condition?</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94284:7"/>
            <p>Is there no other way to prevent the Inconveniences that may happen by a Standing Army, and Officers being chosen Parliament Men in another Reign, but by exposing this? Had they not acted much more like true Patriots to have oblig'd his present Majesty by their Zeal and Affection for his Service, to have put them into such Posts as might have made them more Capable of preventing those Evils they fear, than ever now they are like to be? Must they because they are not imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themselves, which perhaps is none of his Majesty's fault, or that the Law does not allow it, must they therefore embroil his Affairs? Don't they know that in case his present Majesty should either be dethron'd, or cut off by a violent Death, (which God forbid) that the Jacobites, and the high-flown Party of the Church, are like to have the Ascendant, and that they are sworn Enemies, not only to a Commonwealth, but to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient English Constitution? What Hopes then can they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of a Commonwealth, or of having the Grievances they now complain of, redress'd in such a Case? Don't they know, and hear every Day, that most of the Clergy are against Liberty of Conscience, and the Form of Government that they plead for? And have they not giv'n such Instances of their Levity, as shews that most of 'em are not to be trusted? Of about Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Clergymen, or as some will have it near that number of benefic'd Men in <hi>England,</hi> don't they know that there are not above Two Thousand that adheard to the true English Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, after King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Restoration; but all the rest swore to the Slavish Doctrine of Passive Obedience and Nonresistance, and many of 'em preach'd it up as necessary to be believ'd in order to Salvation? Of all that number again, who had so sworn and preach'd, there were scarcely Two Hundred that held out, but contrary to their said Oaths and Doctrine, submitted to the present Government, many of them cheating themselves and the Publick with the knavish Distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a King <hi>de Jure,</hi> and <hi>de Facto,</hi> as they cheat the Church by signing her Doctrinal Articles, not as the Articles of their own Faith, but as Articles of Peace. What Confidence then can be put in those Men? What Reason have we to think that they would not with less Reluctancy declare for the late
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94284:8"/> King <hi>James</hi> again, if he appear'd in <hi>England</hi> with a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Force, than ever they declar'd for King <hi>William,</hi> whose Right they have never recogniz'd by any Act of their Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, nor have they laid their Nonjurant Brethren, or those that absolv'd the Assassins, under any Ecclesiastical Censure; tho' they were ready enough to do so against Dissenters. The Case then being thus, the Commonwealth Party must necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be ruin'd if this Government be overturn'd; and not only so, but all our English Liberties eternally lost.</p>
            <p>Upon all which it does naturally follow, that it is the part of every true Englishman and good Protestant, rather to think of Expedients how to render the present Government Impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and Secure against Violence from without, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery from within; how to enable the Nation to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves at home, and succour their Protestant Brethren abroad; how to put <hi>England</hi> in such a Condition, that as she has broke the Chains from off the Necks of all the Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> she may also cut the Cords of the Ungodly Crew that draw long and deep Furrows upon the Back of the Reformed Churches, and have ungratefully begun a New Persecution upon our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Germany,</hi> who had assisted them to Recover their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Liberty: But instead of that happy Temper and Disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit, here's a Crew of Violent Churchmen on the one hand, and a Club of Factious Dissenters on the other; that make it their whole Business to run down the Presbyterians, as if the Nation were only in Danger from them; and here's the Papists and Jacobites on the one hand, and a parcel of Pretended-Commonwealths-Men on the other, that are undermining the present Government, as if there were no Tyranny or Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon our Liberties to be fear'd, but from thence. These are exactly the Measures our Enemies would have us to take, and the only Methods by which they can effect our Ruine. They have thrown an Apple of Disco d into the Empire of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> by stirring up the Treacherous Papists to invade the Rights of the Protestants, contrary to the Fundamental Laws of the Empire: They have divided the Kingdom of <hi>Spain</hi> by means of their Bribes, and Biggotted Clergy; and there's no Reason to doubt but they have a hand in our Divisions here;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94284:8"/> it being easie enough for them to find Tools for their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, in all the different Parties of which this Nation is compos'd; especially, considering the Number of those that still profess themselves to be for the Late King, and that it was only to preserve their Estates and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that many others have submitted to his present Majesty.</p>
            <p>It is high time I should come now to consider the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of this Pamphlet. It begins as if the Gentlemen who compos'd it had been in their Altitudes when the Ground-Plot was laid. <hi>If any Man</hi> (say they) <hi>doubts whether a Standing-Army is Slavery, Popery, Mahometism, Paganism, or any any thing, which they please, let him read,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Passion wherewith this Commencement appears to have been writ, promises but little of solid Reason, from what is to follow. It perfectly bespeaks the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors to have been in Frantick Fits, and that the Thoughts of a Standing Army did so turn their Heads, that they knew not what they writ or said. What Man in his right Wits can think otherwise, to hear Men cry out, that a Standing Army is Slavery, Popery, Mahoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where is the Slavery in <hi>Holland,</hi> a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, though they have had a Standing Army for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years, are they not the freest People perhaps in the World? Where's the Popery, Mahometism, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi>'s Dominions? yet the Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Prince his Father, of Glorious Memory, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver without one; nor has the present Elector cashier'd his, since the Peace. I have neither Time, nor is it worth while to turn to the Stories of <hi>Matho</hi> and <hi>Spendius</hi> at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage;</hi> nor need we go so far back as the Mamalukes of <hi>Egypt;</hi> that of a latter Sultan depos'd by his Janisaries, is fresh in Memory. Their Instances of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> is foreign to the Purpose; there the Prince and the People
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94284:9"/> differ'd in Religion; the Spaniards were animated by the Priests, against the Protestants, which, blessed be God, is not our Case. Our Prince is the greatest Protector, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, of the Protestant Faith. We are not to fear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Incroachment upon us on that Account. And the same Answer may serve for all their Instances in the Late Reigns.</p>
            <p>Our Princes were Papists, or govern'd by such, and were besides preach'd into Tyranny and Despotical Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by our Clergy: They had no Cause to fear an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from <hi>France,</hi> because they were embarqu'd in the same Interest and Design with that Crown. They were so far from endeavouring to prevent the Slavery of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and the Ruine of the Protestant Religion, that they contributed to both; nor were their Titles controverted by their Subjects, and an opposite Title maintain'd by a mighty Potentate. There was no Prince then beyond Sea that laid Claim to their Crown, or had a French and Irish Army at their Beck, whenever Opportunity offered to assert it, So that it was evident and plain that they could have no other work for a Standing Army, but to enslave their own Subjects. But they must be wilfully blind that don't perceive the Case to be otherwise now: Here we have a Prince that is the Object of the Malice of Popery and Tyranny, because he hath put a Stop to the Career of Both. He rescued his Native Country from them, when a Stripling, and is not yet allow'd time to breathe, since he hath delivered all <hi>Europe</hi> from them, and fought its Deliverance thro' Seas of Blood: Yet this is the only Tyrant we are now to dread; and his Army that knock'd off our Chains, are the only Men that will put them on again. A grateful Reward to a gallant Prince and a valiant Army!</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94284:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Brisac</hi> is still detain'd by <hi>France,</hi> contrary to the Treaty: They threaten Military Execution upon the Protestants of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> for claiming the Freedom of their Religion, according to the Fundamental Laws of the Empire. They have Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Armies ready to Invade <hi>Italy, Spain, Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> as soon as the King of <hi>Spain</hi> dies. They solicit to have that Succession settled on one of the Princes of <hi>France,</hi> contrary to as solemn a Treaty and Renuntiation as was ever made in the World. Yet <hi>England</hi> has no cause to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any thing, either from their Force or their Fraud; tho we have Villanous Assassins at home ready to murder our King on every opportunity, and unnatural Rebells enough to invite over a <hi>French</hi> Army, to restore their old Mr. when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Blow can be given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do these Gentlemen think that all the Assassins fell in <hi>Charnock, Perkins</hi> and <hi>Keys,</hi> or that all the Conspirators that sollicited for the Great Blessing of a <hi>French</hi> Invasion were Executed with <hi>Fenwick</hi> and <hi>Friend.</hi> Is their no Earl still alive, whose Horses may be borrowed for a <hi>Turnham-Green</hi> Expedition? Are the Clergy-men buried that absolved the Assassins, and told them, <hi>That going up to a Cart under</hi> Tyburn <hi>was the first step to Heaven?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there no Great Prince in the World that owes King <hi>William</hi> a Grudge for making him Disgorge his Conquests, and balking his Design of the Universal Monarchy? Is there no old Cuff in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, that can Consecrate a Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to Stab a Prince that hath hindered the enlarging of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Patrimony? Is there no old Angry Prince alive that had Sir <hi>Edmunbury Godfery</hi> Strangled, for taking the Disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi>'s Throte Cut, because he formerly knew too much of his Measures? And is their no <hi>Cranburn</hi> or <hi>Keys</hi> that will do him the Service to be Orderly Men to dogg his Rival, in order to Murder him? Is there no Young <hi>Perkin</hi> beyond-Sea, that may make a Match for a Daughter of <hi>F.</hi> and lay the Foundation of future Titles and Invasions? Have no <hi>Fr.</hi> Wh—s come over of late that were well versed in the mystery of Ploting in the days of <hi>Yore?</hi> and have they forgot what influence prostitution had of old to gain some Men to their Party? Are there no angry Clergymen in the Kingdom, that bear King <hi>Willam</hi> a Grudg,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94284:10"/> because he was born in a Commonwealth? is descended of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors that never believed one word of the Doctrine of Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Obedience? Is there none of 'em bear him ill will because he was bred amongst <hi>Dutch</hi> Presbyterians? hath restored Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytry in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and given Liberty of Conscience in <hi>England.</hi> Is there none of the Faction remaining that branded all the Religions, and Sobermen of the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the name of Trimers, and Presbyterians in Masquerade, that Preach'd from their Pulpits they loved the Papists better than they did them, and that ridiculed the belief of Popish Plots? Are there none who use endeavours to divide the moderate Church of <hi>England-men,</hi> and the Dissenters among themselves, because they know they are King <hi>William</hi>'s Strength, and that thro their sides they might wound him under the fifth Ribb? If there be none of those things in Nature, then we stand in need of no defence, we may beat our Spears into Plowshares and our Swords into Pruning-hooks; but if their be such things, then let the World judge what Friends they are to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Interest, and the Welfare of <hi>England,</hi> that would have us deprived of a Land-force in our present Circumstances.</p>
            <p>It were to be wished that these Men in their Lucid Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals would be pleased to consider, whether it be impossible for our Fleet ever to be surprized in a Harbour, as it well nigh happened not many years ago; whether they may not be wind-bound upon our own Coasts, whilst that of our Enemies is brought upon us, as our Fleet was in <hi>Plimouth</hi> Harbour, when the <hi>Spanish</hi> Armada came into the Channel, and had not God Infatuated them, and made the Stars in their Courses to fight against them, might have blockt us up there whilst the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> had Landed his Army in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They would do well likewise to consider whether a certain Prince, who was never a Slave to his Word, and seldom misses to lay hold of his opportunitys, would not think it a very good one to revenge himself upon a Prince and Nation, that have broke all his Political and Ecclesiastical Measures, if once he found them without a Defence, and could a better oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity be desired than to have him and his Parliament set at Variance; his Troops disbanded against his Will, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple possessed with an opinion that he designs to enslave them: Yet these are the things, this Pamphlet drives at, whether the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94284:10"/> Authors have touch'd any Lewidors or not may be worth the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, for some Passages in their Book make it very sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious.</p>
            <p>Page 19. <q rend="margQuotes">They tell us that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, when he Landed, set forth all the Oppressions of the last Reign <hi>[but the keeping up a standing Army]</hi> declared for a free Parliament in which things were to be so settled that there should be no danger of falling again into sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and promised to send back all his Foreign Forces as soon as this was done,</q> By which they would insinuate that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways design'd a standing Army, and that he hath broke his promise in not sending home his Foreign Troops, But can these Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have the confidence to say that we are hitherto delivered from the danger of falling back into that very Slavery, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that same Prince too, from which he deliver'd us, do they not remember how near the Fatal blow was being given to the most valuable Life in the whole World, but a few years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, and that the late King with a <hi>French</hi> Army was come as far as <hi>Callis</hi> before ever we heard of him, and was immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have Embarked upon a signal from <hi>Dover</hi> Clifts, or a Message that King <hi>William</hi> was murder'd, and that <hi>Fenwick Friend,</hi> and the rest of the Jacobites were to have joyn'd him upon his Landing: And is not a great Potentate in the World more at leisure now to second and countenance such an Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than he was then? did it not appear at the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the Plotters, that he would have sent an Army to ioyn them sooner, if he had not been diverted with so many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>sur le bras</hi> to use their own Term, all at once? does not the raging fury of the Papists against the Protestants in <hi>France, Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> smell strong of an irreconcilable hatred and Hellish rancour against the Reformed Religion and its known Champion? does not that horrid division that they have sown in the Empire between the Papists and Protestants there deprive us of all hopes of assistance from our Allies beyond Sea? and does not these ill tim'd ad fiery suggestions contain'd in this Pamphlet against his Majesty and his Administrations, all look as if there were a design in hand; not only to deprive King <hi>William</hi> of the assistance of his Friends beyond Sea, but to render him suspected to his Friends on this side, and is it he alone that they aim at, or is it not the Protestant Interest which he hath so gallantly deffended,</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94284:11"/>
            <p>In the 20th. Page they are very angry that the Article in our Declaration of Right, which says, <q rend="margQuotes">That the raising and keeping up an Army in time of Peace, is contrary to Law. Had these words tagg'd to it, <hi>Without Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> as if, say they, the consent of the Parliament would not have made it Legal without those words, or that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent would make it less dangerous,</q> But by these Gentlemens leave if it be not a mighty presumption to offer to argue with them that so much despise the Wisdom of that Convention to which we owe the settlement of all the liberty we enjoy, 'tis very plain there may be a Case when 'tis necessary for a Parliament to give their Consent to the raising or keeping up of a standing Army in time of Peace, as Information of a design to invade us from abroad or of a Plot to bring us into Confusion at home, and this may be done without any danger to the Peoples Liberty, whereas, if it be performed without Consent of Parliament, it must needs be Itroductive of Tyranny,</p>
            <p>Page. 20. <q rend="margQuotes">They insist upon the mismanagement of affairs du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as if they had a mind to charge the Rebellion there upon his Majesty, as that of 41 was charged upon his Grandfather, for <hi>p.</hi> 21. they tell us the Jacobites in those early days, said that same ill Councellers design'd to play the same Game again of a standing Army, and attributed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly the neglect of <hi>Ireland</hi> to the same Cause, because by that Omission it was made necessary to raise a greater Army to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it, with which the King acquainted the Parliament the 8th, of <hi>March,</hi> and declared he thought it not advisable to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the reducing it with less than 20000 Horse and Foot. This was a bitter Pill to the Parliament who thought they might have managed their share of the War with <hi>France</hi> at Sea, but there was no Remedy, a greater Army must be rais'd or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> lost, and to gild it, all the Courtiers usher'd in their speeches with this Declaration that they would be the first for disbanding them when the War was over. <hi>p.</hi> 22. Thus the Wars in <hi>Ireland</hi> was nurs'd up, either thro' Chance, Inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, or the necessity of our Affairs (for I am unwilling to think it was design) for at last it was grown so big, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing less than his Majesties great Genius, and the usual success that always attends his Conduct, could have overcome it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Then they tell us that the Parliament found Commissary <hi>Shales</hi> to be the cause of a great part of the Miscarriages, prayed his Majesty to acquaint who it was that advised the imploying him,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94284:11"/> which his Majesty did not remember, that before <hi>Shales</hi> could be brought to <hi>England,</hi> the Parliament was prorogued, and after dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and <hi>Shales</hi> soon after died. The neglect of <hi>Ireland</hi> this Year, (say they) made it necessary to raise more Forces, which afterwards on pretence of Invading <hi>France,</hi> was advanced to 87698 Men. They say also that the people of <hi>Ireland</hi> demanded Arms, and Commissions to be sent them, which in all probability would have made the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of that Kingdom very easie; and that in the Army raised for the reducing of <hi>Ireland,</hi> very few Gentlemen of Estates there could get Imployments, tho' they were in a miserable Condition here, and made their utmost Application for them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let any man judge to what purpose all this matter is rak'd together if it be not to render his Majesty Odious, and to possess the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with an opinion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that he suffer'd the Affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi> to come to that extremity, on purpose that he might have an Army rais'd, which is in plain English to make him Guilty of all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant blood that was shed, and of all the Rapine and Spoil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in that Kingdom, and that to prevent the Parliaments enquiry into it, he dissolved them.</p>
            <p>I have heard of a Crew about Town that drink healths to him that shall cut of the next King's-Head, and I think it plain by this heavy Charge that some men have a great mind to be at acting the like Tragedy once more, but upon enquiry, I believe it will be found that whereas some of those that were formerly concerned were great, pretenders to Religion, the Boutefeus and Incendiaries of the present time, will be found Jacks, Libertines, Deists, and Socinians, and whether such persons be incapable of receiving Bribes fcom Foreign or Domestick Enemies, to raise divisions amongst us: Let those who know any think of the Virtuous disposition, and the untainted Honour. of .... one of the mighty pretenders for a Commonwealth, and the great Oracle of some Fools of the Party, determine. Is it not a shame that a person whom his Native Country hath vomited out for his Odious Heresies should be so much Caress'd here by some people. Let them enquire amongst all that have known him from his Youth, into his Weathercock temper of Religion, and Commendable Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, and then let them judge according to evidence, whether such a man as he may not be hired to do any sort of mischief: This I think enough to be a warning to the Wise to avoid such Company. We have no reason to think, that such as are Enemies to reveal'd Religion, are proper to consult as the Oracles of the Nation. The Liberty they plead for is meer Licentiousness, and it may perhaps be worth the inquiry whether the act against Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94284:12"/> and Prophaneness Last Sessions, hath not prompted them by this means to seek a Revenge on the Nation. I have heard that they threatned when that act was Passing, to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on some thrt promoted it, and we cannot but think their Rancour extends to his Majesty that sign'd it, and we may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guess at the Orthodoxy of the Authors of this Pamphlet, by their seeming to deny the Depravation of Humane Nature in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and saying, Pag 18, <hi>That the Domination of the Church,</hi> is the worst part of Popery, tho' I think all true Protestants will say, that the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Doctrine of Justification by works which renders the Death and Merit of our Saviour of no use, are worse than her Domination, tho' that be bad enough, and worse indeed than we have words to Express it, but any Religion provided they be not curb'd in their Licentious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctises will go down with those that are against Reveal'd Religion, And here I cannot pass over their malicious Reflection upon the Clergy in General, to whom they say, <hi>Popery was not so formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a thing, but with a little Cookery it might have been rendred palatable.</hi> I have said enough already to convince the Gentlemen, that I am no admirer of the Passive Obedience Clergymen, and shall say further, That I believe the Kings and the Nations greatest E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, are amongst that Crew and their followers, and if our Authors had taken asi much pains to trace the Miscarriages of our Affairs up to the Fountain, as they have been at to Charge them upon his Majesty and the Court, they would perhaps have found that they were originally owing to the Disciples of Passive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but at the same time I think my self obliged in Conscience and Justice to say that such moderate Churchmen as his Majesty hath advanced to the Episcopal Dignity since his coming to the Crown, and the Inferiour Clergy of their sentiments who are not a few, and always understood Passive Obedience, in a sound and limited sence, would rather have gone to the Stake then have digested Popery tho' nev e so well cook'd, either by Antichrist's or Bishop's <hi>Laud</hi>'s Disciples.</p>
            <p>But to return again to our <hi>Irish</hi> Affairs: Now that these Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have discharged their Choler, do they think the Nation have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, that his Majesties Affairs were betray'd there, by Lieutenant General <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and that other person, for trusting of whom to the apparent ruin of his Majesty's Interest, Mr. <hi>Temple</hi> did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards unhappily drown himself? Do they think that the Nation will be gall'd with such stuff, that Parliament thought they could have managed their share of the War against <hi>France</hi> by Sea, when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94284:12"/> the <hi>French</hi> defeated our Squadron at <hi>Bantry</hi> Bay, Landed an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my afterwards in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and possess'd themselves of all the strong Towns in that Kingdom. Is it supposeable that the King suffered matters to come to that Crisis in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that he might thereby get an opportunity of raising an Army, when the Progress of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Irish</hi> was such as well nigh threatned the loss of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two Kingdoms? Why don't these Gentlemen say that he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd himself at the same time to be wounded by the <hi>French</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, and suffered his Fleet to be defeated by Monsieur <hi>de Tourville</hi> at the same time, for that same end too, and to give credit to the Argument, which they mention P. 22. <hi>That a Fleet is no security to us.</hi> Can any reasonable person think that it was a pleasure to his Majesty to be reduc'd to a necessity of going to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and thereby to give the <hi>French</hi> an opportunity of Invading <hi>England,</hi> as they might easily have done had not God prevented it after the defeat of our Fleet under Admiral <hi>Torrington,</hi> do they think that it was a pleasure for his Majesty to be in <hi>Ireland</hi> when the <hi>French</hi> were so formidable in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and did so much endanger his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country of <hi>Holland,</hi> with the Care and Government of which he is also entrusted: what reason can these Gentlemen assign why <hi>Flanders</hi> should not be look'd upon to be the Natural Barrier of <hi>England</hi> now as well as in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>s time, and that we are not as much concern'd in the defence of that Country now as then. If they will allow themselves a little freedom of thought, they may speedily be convinced that we are much more concerned to defend it now than then, In those days, it was the Power of <hi>Spain</hi> that terrified all <hi>Europe;</hi> but <hi>Philip</hi> the II. could not bring Vast Armies by Land into <hi>Flanders;</hi> as the <hi>French</hi> King now can do, so that there was no such reason to be afraid of him as we have now to be afraid of the <hi>French,</hi> who if they had the Seaports of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> once in possession, and that they might soon accomplish if <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> stood Neuter, or did not assist the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> any otherwise than by Sea, we must quickly submit our Necks to the Gallican Yoak, our Merchants could stir no where but they must become their Prize, they might considering their own strength at Sea, and the accession it would thereby receive be able to cope with our Fleet, and Invade us by Land when they pleased. With what reason then can these Gentlemen advance that the Parliament thought they could manage their part of the War with <hi>France</hi> by Sea, can any man be so little sensible of the true Interest of <hi>England</hi> as to think that we should sit still, and tamely look on whilst the <hi>French</hi> swallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> I remember indeed that this was the usual
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94284:13"/> Topick insisted on by the <hi>Jacobites</hi> in publick Company, what were we concerned with <hi>Flanders.</hi> How would it affect us if <hi>Namure,</hi> &amp;c. were in Ashes; what had we to do to send Forces thither? and now it seems, this Republican Club as they would have the World believe them to be, are become the <hi>Jacobites</hi> Eccho, and its well if there be not <hi>Jacobites</hi> in masquerade among them, tho' I think there's little need of any such disguise when some of the Hot-heads are not ashamed openly to profess that they look for better things from the known <hi>Jacobites,</hi> than from the Whiggs.</p>
            <p>We have the more ground for this suspicion, when these Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tell us <hi>page</hi> 24. That at the opening of the last Sessions of Parliament, <hi>a New Plot was said to be discovered for murdering the King, and searches were made at midnight through the whole City, to the discovery of plenty of Fornication, but no Traitors.</hi> What then it seems the Court now have learned the art of making Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plots, as well as the Courts in former times, a handsome sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion! Have our pretended Commonwealth Club learned the art of ridiculing Plots, from their Brethren the Tories, was their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any such thing as a Plot to murder the King, it's pity but that some of the Authors of such Raillery should be obliged to do Penance for ridiculing the Plot at the Gallows, where the Assassins confessed it: Are our Jacobites so much reformed for the better, that they are not capable of such an Execrable design now, as well as two or three years ago, will our pretended Commonwealth-Club become their Vouchers, then I hope the Jacobites will be so kind to them on the other hand as to undertake that they will cut off no more Kings by a wrested form of Law: Then e'en let it be so, with all my heart, so have I seen two Scabbed Jades Nab on another with great pleasure for a while, till they came to touch to the Quick and then fell at last to determine the Controversie with their Heels after having sounded a Charge with the Trumpets of their Tails? Well, but it seems the searchers did not lose all their labour for they discovered plenty of Fornication, which our honest Club think fit to make a Jest of, and that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother proof of their good morals; but in truth, I know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son why a pretended Socinian Commonwealth's-man should scruple the Commission of that or any other Crime, more than a Popish or Protestant King <hi>James</hi>'s man, and perhaps a Love to Licentious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is the principal Tie of their present Union,</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94284:13"/>
            <p>Others will tell 'em that there is a certain Prince in the World who invaded a neighbouring Country for having given him <hi>ill Satisfaction,</hi> and is it not reasonable to think that Natural Ambition, and desire of Revenge may prompt such an one more strongly to Invade a Kingdom, that hath giv'n him an open and avowed Dissatisfaction? Was there never any such thing as a Massacre in <hi>France</hi> carried on under Pretence of a Marriage-Treaty, and a <hi>Pontifex Necem Colinii probat</hi> writ upon the Pope's Windows to justifie the Lawfulness of it? And is <hi>Rome</hi> become now so tender-hearted, and of such a Puritanical Conscience, that she could not for such a good Cause, as the Extirpating the Northern Heresie, give a <hi>Pontifex Angliae conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pulationem probat,</hi> notwithstanding a Publick Treaty?</p>
            <p>Their Reflections upon the Proceedings of Parliament about the Standing Army, and upon the King and Court, as having acted therein contrary to the Act of Parliament, and their own Promise, are fitter to be censur'd by the Government than ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of here. But be the Matters of Fact they alledge true or false, it signifies little to the Matter in debate; for if it be true that we have a treacherous Party to deal with at Home and Abroad, and that we are as much under a Necessity of preventing the <hi>Netherlands</hi> being swallow'd up by <hi>France,</hi> as we should be under of helping to quench the Flames in our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's House, lest it should afterwards consume our own. The Necessity of a Land-Force is uncontrovertible, and therefore the Government ought not to be lash'd by every virulent Pen, for rewarding those that are so good Patriots to their Country, as to oppose the Current of Jacobites and others against it, <hi>that being the only way to hinder our Enemies from effecting that in Time of Peace that they could never effect in Time of War.</hi> And I am confident every honest and thinking Man will agree, that when His Majesty so positively declar'd that the Posture of Affairs abroad did require a Land-Force for some time; his Opinion is to be taken, and his Judgment to be relied on sooner than that of a mix'd Club of Socinians, Jacobites, and Pretended Republicans, who, for any thing appears as yet to the contrary, seem more likely to be influenc'd by Papists and Jacobites, and others, that have a mind to embroil our Affairs, and to bring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94284:14"/> those that are for a Commonwealth under the Hatred of the Publick, than to be allowed or encouraged by those that think that Form of Government the best.</p>
            <p>Besides, we may plainly see that it is not His Majesty and the Court alone that thinks a Land-Force requisite for our Safety, but the Wisdom of the Three Nations met in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have concurr'd in it; and tho' the Number allow'd be not so great as perhaps the Court might have desir'd, yet it is sufficient to convince the Nations that the Parliaments of all Three think a Land-Force necessary; and certainly their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is preferable to that of our Authors, some of whom, I am apt to think, have little or no Estate to be tax'd</p>
            <p>One would think it were enough to convince any reasonable Man, that there's ground to suspect a mischievous Design at the bottom of all this Clamour against a Standing Army, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Jacobites in Parliament, and every where else, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd so mightily for disbanding the Whole; which certainly they would never have been, had they not hop'd to find their Account in it. And besides, the common Prudence and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of Nations never allow of any such thing, whilst those that were their Enemies continue in a Posture of Offence. Their Objection that we had so long time decried the Power of <hi>France,</hi> and publish'd her declining Condition, is nothing to the purpose. It has now been seen by those that formerly would not believe it; and if all our Confederates had been true to the Alliance, the World would soon have had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Proof of it: But that Opportunity being lost, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solation and Poverty of <hi>France</hi> may give just Cause of Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie to her Neighbours, that she will be under a Necessity to over-run them with her numerous Troops of starving Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, who have nothing left them to subsist on at Home; the Poverty of the Goths and Vandals having been none of the least Causes of their seeking for Entertainment abroad when they could not have it at home. Tho' <hi>France</hi> be comparatively ruin'd to what she was Thirty Years ago, she is strong enough still to ruine <hi>England,</hi> if she have no Diversion elsewhere; which one Point, well consider'd, would stop all the Clamour some
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94284:14"/> ill-minded People have rais'd against His Majesty's going beyond Sea, and spending a little Money there at this Juncture, in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terviews and Conferences with neighbouring Princes and States. We are not so strong, nor well united at Home, as not to stand in need of an Alliance Abroad; but such is the cursed Temper of some People in this Nation, that they love to disseminate and entertain Jealousies of a Prince, both in Relation to Church and State, whom the whole Protestant World besides look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be the main Support of their Cause, under God, to whom they pour out ardent Prayers every Day for his Preservation and long Life; and we see the most Zealous of the Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had such an Opinion of his refin'd Vertue, that they trusted him with the Command of their Armies, as <hi>Generalissimo;</hi> which put such an Opportunity into his hand, that had he been of such a boundless Ambition as those Men would give out, the Universal Monarchy seem'd in a manner to be at his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; which I think is enough to convince any Man, that his own Subjects have no just Cause to suspect him.</p>
            <p>The only Objection of value, that can be rais'd against a Land-Force, in our present Circumstances, is the ill use that may be made of them in case of his Majesty's Death, and the Inability of the Country to maintain them; but its hop'd it does not sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the Wisdom of an English Parliament to find out proper Expedients to obviate both these Inconveniencies. If the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be put into the Hands of such as the People love, and trust, and are known to be Men of true English Principles; if the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers be carefully taught their Duty, and instructed in the Grounds of the Protestant Religion, by Clergymen of honest Principles; and if a good Discipline be kept among 'em, or that in case of no Military Imployment happen for them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Time limited for their being kept up, or till the Militia be so regulated and disciplin'd, as they may be capable of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending their Country. If, I say, in that case the Parliament in their Wisdom shall think fit to employ them in publick Works, for the good of the Nation, all those Fears about them will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanish; and instead of being chargeable, they may be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to their Country; whereas Idleness hath in all Ages prov'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94284:15"/> fatal to Armies, of which <hi>Hanibal</hi>'s at <hi>Capua,</hi> is one great and well-known Instance.</p>
            <p>As to those Mens Project, of leaving us in our present Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, without any other Defence than the Milita, though it cannot be deny'd, but that their Limbs and natural Courage may be as good as that of the Standing Army, yet the faint Resistance they made to the Dutch at <hi>Chattam,</hi> whilst one Regiment of disciplin'd Scotch did such Wonders there, and the Consterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Nation was in when naked of disciplin'd Troops, upon breaking out of the Plot here against the King's Life, and the Fears of an Invasion from <hi>France,</hi> are enough to stop the Mouths of all Gainsayers. No Man who has look'd into History, but knows that the Roman Veterane Legions, and <hi>Alexander the Great</hi>'s disciplin'd Troops, were too hard for all the Nations that ever encountred them, though many of them were nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to them in natural Courage.</p>
            <p>It were endless to run through all the Insinuations of that Libel; nor will Time allow me to say any thing further, and therefore, after having acquainted the Reader that I have had no Time to digest my Thoughts upon the Subject, he must not think it strange if I fall short of his Expectation in answering all the Particulars of that Pamphlet; which is the Product of a Club, and the Result of their Mature Deliberations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:94284:15"/>
            <head>Postscript.</head>
            <p>AFter the finishing of what goes before, another Paper came to hand, Entituled <hi>Considerations on the Choice of a Speaker,</hi> &amp;c. which being writ, as 'tis supposeable, by the same Party, and directed to the same end, of creating a Misunderstanding betwixt the King and the People, I thought might deserve some Animadversions.</p>
            <p>All the Arguments and Suggestions therein contained, proceed upon this Supposition, That the King and Court carry on a distinct Interest from that of the Country, in desiring a Land-Force for a limited Time: The False<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of which I think is sufficiently demonstrated al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; it being certainly the Interest of the Country to have a Defence, and not to expose themselves to the Insults of a Foreign and Intestine Enemy, for want of Regular Troops. If indeed those whom we have most cause to fear, had no other Forces to attack us with, but Country Militia, or could not have any other in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, whenever Opportunity offers, there were no need of keeping a Land-Force standing in <hi>England:</hi> but see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is known that they have a Numerous Army of the best disciplin'd Men in <hi>Europe,</hi> those who press with so much Violence to have all our Troops disbanded, seem to have an Interest in view, distinct from that of their Country.</p>
            <p>The Matter then being so, it can be no sufficient Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to refuse such a Person for <hi>Speaker,</hi> as is grateful
<pb facs="tcp:94284:16"/> to His Majesty, or perhaps has some Employment under him, if another cannot be found who is equally capable and grateful both to King and People. It is none of my Business to meddle with the Characters of those Persons whom this Paper seems to reflect upon; only thus much I may venture to say, that I am afraid the Gentlemen who are the Authors of it would be as much at a Loss, were it left to their Choice, to name a Speaker to please themselves, as they would be to condescend upon a Form of Government, were the present Frame of our Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution dissolv'd, and they at Liberty to choose one out of all their own Utopian Models.</p>
            <p>It must needs be a Disservice to the Country, to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and foment Jealousies at this time betwixt King and People. His Majesty fits at the Helm, sees further into the Posture of Affairs, and Intrigues of Foreign Courts, than it's possible for any one else to do; and seeing there's no Reason to think that he will advise to any thing but what is for the Interest of that Country he hath so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ventured his Life to deliver, and make free; they who oppose themselves to a Speaker that may be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him, do just as if unexperienc'd Mariners should refuse a Pilot that an experienc'd Captain knows, and can put Confidence in, because they think he is too much in the Captain's Interest, and may, perhaps, by forcing him to accept one of their liking, run upon those very Shelves that they thought to avoid.</p>
            <p>Our Enemies cannot desire a better Opportunity against us, than that which a Division betwixt the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will afford them; therefore it seems to be the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dispensible Duty of all that wish well to their Country, to endeavour Expedients for promoting an Union; but certainly they don't take such Measures, who so positive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:94284:16"/> write against chusing a Speaker that may be in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Interest. We had reason indeed to oppose former Princes in that matter; but, blessed be God, we have a King now, who hath on all Occasions demonstrated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to be <hi>Pater,</hi> and not <hi>pestis Patriae,</hi> as some of them were; and seeing our Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> who are as much concern'd, and perhaps as zealous to seek the Welfare of their Country as we possibly can be, have thought fit to submit to his Majesty's Desires, as that which they are sensible is absolutely necessary for their own Safety; let it never be said, that <hi>England,</hi> who was the first that invited him over, and contributed most to assist him in working out our common Deliverance, shall now only become suspicious of his Conduct, and prove Froward and Refractory, at the Instigation of a Parcel of Men, who make it their Sport and Recreation to throw Darts and Firebrands about, and perhaps, upon a thorow Enquiry, will be found, neither to have more Zeal for, nor greater Interest in their Country than other People, but are rather of that Roman Consul's Mind, <hi>who thought there could be no such thing as Liberty, except People had an Allowance to ruine themselves if they had a mind to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>